这是事情有点偏离轨道的地方。
This is where things go a little off the rails.
我们将谈论免费。
We're going to talk about Free.
完全公开，Free Monads 通常不是你想要的 [笑] 但是
And full disclosure, Free Monads are usually not what you want [LAUGH] but
他们解决了一个非常具体的问题，很高兴了解和
they solve a very specific problem and it's good to know about and
当我们谈论功能架构时。
when we're talking about functional architecture.
我们讨论了 monad 转换器堆栈，我们讨论了自由 monad。
We talked about monad transformer stacks and we talked about free monads.
我们讨论了这些阅读器类型注入。
And we talked about like these reader type injections.
我们看到了通过 ask 进行的读者注入或通过 ask 进行的依赖注入。
We saw reader injection through ask or dependency injection through ask.
我只想向您展示一个使用 Free 的示例。
And I just wanna show you an example of using Free.
事实证明，
And it actually turns out,
这是我想要构建的第一个应用程序的最佳解决方案。
it was the best solution to the first app that I wanted to build.
所以值得了解。
So it's worthwhile to know.
那么，什么是自由的，自由的 monad？
So, what is free, the free monad?
免费的 monad 是一种获取函数并将它们视为数据类型的方法。
The free monad is a is a way to take your functions and treat them like data types.
所以如果我有一个像 HTTP GET 这样的函数，它需要一些
So if I have a function like HTTP GET and it takes some
像 URL 这样的参数，而不是它去和
arguments like a URL, instead of it going and
做一个任务并尝试喜欢，现在就去做这个功能，
making a task and trying to like, go do this function right now,
我们实际上可以返回一个数据类型，比如保存 URL 的 HttpGet。
we can actually return a data type, like HttpGet holding the URL.
所以你现在有一个数据类型来表示要获取一个 URL。
So you have a data type now that represents going to get a URL.
我们希望它成为 monad 的原因是因为我们想说，
And the reason we want it to be a monad is because we want to say,
好吧，我有这个数据类型，我想链接，对吗？
well, I have this data type, and I want to chain, right?
仿佛它真的做到了。
As if it actually did it.
我想获取该 URL 的内容，并且
And I want to get the contents of that URL, and
我可以使用类似 HTTP POST 的东西。
I could use something like an HTTP POST.
我们会做一些其他的 URL，比如分析，
And we'll do some other URL like analytics,
内容，好吗？
with the contents, all right?
然后，我最终应该得到一个数据结构来表示
And then, what I should end up with is a data structure representing
嵌套的计算树。
the nested tree of computation.
您基本上是在构建 AST。
You're basically building an AST.
您正在将函数提升为数据类型，
You're lifting your functions into datatypes,
将它们视为正在运行，然后您就可以稍后解释它们。
treating them as if they're running and then you're able to interpret them later.
所以现在我们必须创建我们所说的解释器
So now we have to create what we call an interpreter
在这里解释以实际解释状态结构。
interpret over here to actually interpret the status structure.
所以我们实际上要在这里建造它。
So we're actually gonna build this right here.
而我真正想做的是引入一个新的图书馆。
And what I wanna do is actually bringing in a new library.
它被称为达吉。
It's called daggy.
我们要带一些标签，很棒的图书馆，强烈推荐。
We're gonna bring in tag some, great library, highly recommended.
Daggy，它所做的就是我制作的整个课程，例如 HTTP GET，
Daggy, all it does is this whole entire class I was making stuff like HTTP GET,
它取一些值，取一些 x 并作为数据类型返回。
it takes some value, take some x and returns as a data type.
我们有方法。
We have methods on it.
这只是允许我们使用更短的语法来定义这些对象。
This just allows us to, it's in a shorter syntax for defining these objects.
然后它给了我一个功能来分解一组不同的类型和
And then it gives me a function to kind of decompose a set of different types and
我们马上就会看到。
we'll see that in a second.
所以我会说，Daggy 的工作方式是，我们有 http，我们称之为标签总和。
So the way Daggy works is I'll say, we have http and we'll call it tag sum.
所以它就像一个 sum 类型，它就像一个类型定义。
So it's like a sum type, it's like a type definition.
说 HTTP 是超类的名称。
Say HTTP is the name of the superclass kind of thing.
然后我们会说我们有一个 get，而 get 的参数是 x。
Then we're gonna say we have a get, and the arguments get has is x.
网址呢？
How about URL?
然后我们有一个帖子。
And then we have a post.
我们将获得 URL 和正文。
And we'll have the URL and the body.
所以，我们在这里所做的就是说，我定义了两种数据类型 GET 和 POST。
So, what we've done here is say, I've defined two data types GET and POST.
实际上，在我们进一步讨论之前，让我们先看看它。
And actually let's just take a look at that before we go any further.
所以，如果我说 Http，Get，不管怎样，home。
So, if I say Http, Get, whatever, home.
你可以console.log这个东西。
You can console.log this thing.
它就像一个小数据类型
And it's just like a little data type for
我的，自己的用法。
my, Own usage.
看？它有一个小网址主页。
See? It's got a little url home.
所以对于我正在创建的那些大对象文字来说，这是一种更短的语法。
So it's a shorter syntax for those big object literals I was creating.
但它的酷是我可以说，如果我有一个家
But what's cool about it is I'm able to say, if I have a get of home
我可以调用 Cata，它是 Catamorphism 的缩写。
and I can call Cata on that and it's a short for Catamorphism.
我可以做一个模式匹配说，如果它是一个获取，获取 URL 并且
I can do a pattern matching to say, well if it's a get, get the URL out and
做点什么，你好。
do something, hi.
如果是帖子，我有 URL 和
And if it's a post, I have the URL and
我可以使用的身体，我会说，张贴任何东西。
the body at my disposal, I'll say, post whatever.
这两个函数，所以我实际上可以在它上面运行一个 catamorphism 并且
These two functions, so I can actually run a catamorphism on it and
它将模式匹配它是什么类型。
it will pattern match on what type it is.
然后让我解构该类型并对其进行处理。
And then allow me to destructure the type and do something to it.
所以这两个东西一起使用，有点捷径这个小类型
So these two things together will be using, to kinda short cut this little type
创建库，它让我很容易消化和
of creation library and it allows me to easily digest and
匹配而不是像，你有。
match rather than being like, do you have.
否则，我不得不说，我不知道 X 是什么，对吧？
Otherwise, I would have to say like, I don't know what X is, right?
这是get还是post？
Is this a get or a post?
我不确定。
I'm not sure.
如果没有 Cata，我将不得不像，你知道，x 是否有一个身体并且
Without Cata I would have to be like, you know, does x have a body and
它可能又是一次，所以能够在类型上进行模式匹配是件好事。
it's probably again, so it makes it nice to be able to pattern match on the type.
好吧，酷。
All right, cool.
所以我们已经完成了我们的函数获取一个 URL 和
So we've done is taken our functions get with a URL and
使用 URL 和正文发布并使其成为数据类型。
post with the URL and body and made it a data type.
然后我们有一个叫做lift f的小辅助函数，它将它提升到free状态。
Then we have this little helper function called lift f, it lifts it into free.
所以如果我说httpGet，我不能。
So if I say httpGet, I can't.
我能做的就是将这些东西变成单子，只需调用lift F。
What I can do is make these things into monads, just by calling lift F.
这就是为什么它是自由的 monad。
That's why it's the free monad.
它只是提升类型，就像数组是自由幺半群或
It just lifts the type right in, just like an array is the free monoid or
你可以往里面扔任何东西。
you can just throw anything in it.
我们可以用lift F来做到这一点，我们可以拥有这个Get，httpGet。
We can do that with lift F, can we have this Get, httpGet.
然后我们有一个 httpPost，它接受正文中的 URL。
And then we have an httpPost, and it takes the URL in the body.
这当然可以自动化。
And this can certainly be automated.
我们所做的就是运行构造函数，然后立即调用lift F。
All we're doing is running the constructor and then calling lift F right afterwards.
这只是组合。
It's just composition.
但只是试图完整并向您展示这是如何工作的。
But just trying to be complete and show you how this works.
好的，现在让我们在这里实际运行一个小应用程序。
Okay, so now let's actually run a little app here.
所以就像应用程序一样，我们会说首先在家里获取 httpGet。
So like app is, we'll say first get the httpGet on home.
然后我们要把它和内容联系起来。
And then we're gonna chain that with the contents.
是的，我们会用内容来做这篇文章。
And yeah, we'll do this post with the contents.
这不是httpPost，httpPost。
And that's not httpPost, httpPost.
所以只是为了让我们知道，这些小辅助函数实际上是
So just just so we're aware, these little helper functions are literally
只是建设者，我把他们扔进电梯 F。
just the constructors and I'm throwing them into lift F.
所以我们得到的是一个免费的 httpGet，并且
So what we're getting is a free of httpGet, and
这里有一个免费的 httpPost，所以这就是我可以调用链的方式。
a free of httpPost here, so that's how I can call chain.
所以当我调用这个函数时，我可以获得一个免费的 monad，我可以链接这个免费的 monad。
So when I call this function, I can get a free monad, I can chain the free monad.
真正好的一点是免费的 monad 只是数据，
What's really nice about this is free monads aren't anything but data,
它们只是一种数据类型，它只是标准化了一切，
they're just a data type and it just normalizes everything,
我可以串连和作曲，做任何我想做的事。
and I can just chain and compose and do whatever I want.
所以召回结果是上升的。
So recall result is going up.
让我们 console.log 我们这里有什么。
Let's console.log what we have here.
这里发生了什么？
What's going on here?
所以这有点奇怪。
So this is a little weird.
我们有一个自由的 monad，它有一个属性 x 持有我们的 get 对象。
We have a free monad that has a property x is holding our get object.
然后，我们就有了这种延续函数。
And then, we have this kind of continuation function.
所以我们要做的是将它传递给一个解释器。
So we're going to do here is pass this into an interpreter.
我们这样做的方式很有趣。
And the way we do that, it's kind of fun.
如果你有一个免费的，免费的持有一些
If you have a free, free holding some
东西，我们可以免费折叠地图，然后
stuff, we can fold map that out of the free, and
在此之前将其映射到其他类型并映射到其他类型。
map it into some other type before that out of this and into something else.
所以这就是我们要做的。
So that's what we'll do.
我们要做一个小翻译。
We're gonna make a little interpreter.
所以我们有了应用程序，我们将把应用程序映射到解释程序中，然后
So we have the app, and we're gonna fold map the app into interpret, and
让我们做一个小任务吧？
let's make a little task, right?
我们会做一个新的任务，因为这些东西会做一些严肃的事情，对吧？
We'll make a new task because these things are gonna go do serious stuff, right?
实际上，你知道的，我只是想用 ID 把它存根，老实说，
Actually, you know, I'm just gonna use ID to stub it out, honestly,
ID通常是我做的，有点架构，和
ID is typically what I do when I'm, kinda architecting, and
然后当我整理好所有类型时，我将用任务交换 ID，
then when I've got all my types in order, I'll just swap out ID with task,
通过这种方式，我可以实际查看正在发生的事情，而不是将其放在任务中。
this way I can actually look at what's going on instead of having it in a task.
所以我们有了我们的解释，让我们写下来。
So we have our interpret, let's write that.
现在采用我们的类型 x。
Now takes our type x.
再一次，我们将调用我们的 Catamorphism，如果它是一个 get，我们会得到一个 URL。
And again, we gonna call our Catamorphism on that, and if it's a get, we get a URL.
我们为什么不喜欢，您知道，获取您的 URL 并将其放入其中。
Why don't we do like, you know, got your URL and put this in that.
这将是内容
This will be the contents for
这个网址，我们有一个帖子，它需要一个网址和一个正文
this url, and we have a post, and it takes a url and a body
我们会说，将正文发布到此网址。
and we'll say, posted body to this url.
所以，这很有趣。
So, this is interesting.
我们刚刚完成的是我们用数据编写了一个应用程序，并且
What we've just done is we've written an app entirely with data, and
然后我们在调用时决定了我们想要使用的解释器。
then we've decided at the calling time which interpreter we wanna use.
该解释器会将其解释为字符串。
This interpreter will interpret it into strings.
它必须是一个 ID，我们必须在这里有一个目标 monad
It has to be an ID, we have to have a target monad here
因为我们正在调用完整地图，我们希望能够将其放入另一个地图中。
cuz we're calling full map and we want to be able to put it into another.
所以它的Id.of。
So its Id.of.
应该提到，
Should have mentioned that,
我们通常应该有一个目标单子，它几乎总是任务。
we should usually have a target monad, it's almost always task.
但是如果你正在做一些类似的事情，记录一些解释器，
But if you're doing something like these little like, log kind of interpreters,
测试解释器，然后我们就可以做到了。
test interpreters, then we can do that.
现在让我们运行它。
And now let's run it.
我们得到了什么？
And what do we get?
我们得到了我们的想法，所以我们可以调用extract。
We get our idea out so we could just call extract.
看那个。
Look at that.
它发布了供分析之家使用的内容。
It posted the contents for home to analytics.
所以我们已经创建了一个数据结构，我们可以写更多，
So we've we've created a data structure, we could write more on that,
我想我们可以像连锁店一样做更多的电话和
I think we could do like chain we are gonna make more get calls and
无论如何，这只是数据结构和
whatever and it's just the data structure and
然后我们使用 foldMap 解释该数据结构，它只是
then we interpret that data structure using foldMap, which just
级联并运行每条指令并解释它，这很棒。
cascades down and runs each instruction and interprets it, that's great.
任何问题，是的。
Any questions, yes.
&gt;&gt; 所以我们使用 Catamorphism 作为 switch 语句。
&gt;&gt; So we're using the Catamorphism as a switch statement.
&gt;&gt; 是的。 &gt;&gt; 下面还有很多事情要做
&gt;&gt; Yeah. &gt;&gt; There's a lot more going on under
引擎盖，我知道 monad 是什么，但我很好奇你是否对此发表评论。
the hood, I know what the monad is but I'm curious if you comment on that.
我们本质上是用它来做一堆ifs。
We're essentially using it as a way of doing a bunch of ifs.
&gt;&gt; 完全正确。
&gt;&gt; That's totally right.
我们说这个 x 可能是一个 get，也可能是一个 post。
We're saying like this x could be a get, or it could be a post.
JavaScript 并没有给我提供开箱即用的工具，比如，
And JavaScript doesn't give me the tools out of the box to say like,
我有什么样的构造函数？
what kind of constructor do I have?
我会做这个，那个，这个，那个。
I'll do this and that and this and that.
所以这正是它所说的，如果你能做到这一点，
So it's exactly what it's just saying like, if you're get do this,
如果你是后做的。
if you're post do that.
读起来真的很好，这真的很短，所以我不想填满一半
Reads really nice and this is really short so I didn't want to fill up half
屏幕上有喜欢的类或类型，然后尝试编写一个解释器。
the screen with like classes or types and then try to like write an interpreter.
所以这就是我们带狗狗进来的原因，我强烈推荐它。
So that's why we brought doggy in and I highly recommend it.
如果我真的在它到达之前错过它，那就太好了，
It's great if I actually miss this before it even gets there,
我想 daggy 会告诉我的。
I think daggy will tell me.
嘿，你给了我一些东西，你没有在那里发帖。
Hey, you gave me some stuff and you didn't have post in there.
这是非常好的。
That's really nice.
[笑] 就像我试图解释你所说的提前获取和发布和
[LAUGH] Like I tried to interpret your type that said ahead get and post and
你错过了一个案例。
you missed a case.
所以这很酷。
So that's pretty cool.
好的，两秒钟后就是免费的 monad。
All right, so that's free monads in two seconds.
我们实际上会在第一个应用程序中使用它。
We're actually gonna use that for the first app.
我真的很想开车回家，这很有用，
I really wanna drive home that this is useful,
我发现当我们做一个应用程序时它非常有用
I find it very useful when we did an app where we were
当我们拥有 Bower 时将 NPM 推回原位，你们都记得 Bower，这是一个多么美好的世界。
pushing the NPM back when we had Bower, y'all remember Bower, what a world.
无论如何，[笑] 我们喜欢发布 GitHub 包和所有这些东西，
Anyway, [LAUGH] We're like posting like GitHub packages and all this stuff and
我们正在做这一切，就像非常讨厌的过程，有所有这些副作用，
we're doing all this like really nasty processes with all these side effects and
几乎不可能将逻辑与副作用分开。
it was almost impossible to separate the logic from the side effects.
因为这实际上是所有副作用。
Cuz it was literally all side effects.
所以就像，我们如何测试这个东西？
So it was like, how do we test this thing?
我们如何处理这件事？
How do we work with this thing?
我们如何做到这样，我不会每次运行时都向 NPM 发帖
How do we make it so like, I'm not posting to NPM every time I run
就像那样糟透了，就像我真的很想构建这个应用程序一样，但是
it like that sucks, like I really want to build this app out, but
我不想喜欢不小心发布的东西。
I don't want to like accidentally publish things.
这是一个很好的解决方案。
And this was a great solution for that.
然后它就派上用场了，从那以后我就不必再使用它了。
And it came in handy then and then I haven't had to use it since.
[笑] 所以，如果你需要它，它就在你身边，它真的很有用。
[LAUGH] So like, it's there for you if you need it and it's really useful.